Mary Ellen Chase Papers, 1893-1995
Smith College Archives
Mary Ellen Chase Papers
1893-1995
Chase, Mary Ellen, 1887-1973
RG 42 UUID:1693ca76-6fdc-4d17-9785-9a54af9d5ce0
6 boxes (9 linear ft.)
Smith College Archives Northampton, MA
Professor of English and novelist. Contains biographical material, articles, correspondence, photographs, awards, financial information, reviews, and writings.
Mary Ellen Chase was born on February 24, 1887 in Blue Hill, Maine. Her parents were deeply religious Protestants and Mary Ellen was one of eight children who received a thorough biblical education as well as an academic one. She began writing at the age of sixteen and by her death on July 28, 1973, had published more than thirty essays, novels, and biographies.
At the age of nineteen, Chase took a leave from the University of Maine, where she was enrolled as an undergraduate, in order to teach in a one-room school in Buck's Harbor, Maine. Following her graduation, she taught for three years in Wisconsin at a coeducational boarding school and later for two years at a private girls school in Chicago, Illinois. At that point in time, Chase fell ill and was advised by her doctor that a move to Montana would improve her health. During her time there, Chase taught public school and wrote two novels.
Upon full recovery, Chase took a teaching position at the University of Minnesota where she also studied and earned her MA in 1918 and later her Ph.D. in 1922. In 1926 she was hired by Smith College where she taught courses on the English novel and the King James version of the Bible. During her time at Smith, Chase became respected colleague, teacher, and friend to many. Her courses, taken by English majors and non-English majors alike, were some of the most popular on campus. In addition, Chase's home on Paradise Road became a favorite place for her students to go for good conversation and cookies.
Despite her success as an author, teaching remained her true love throughout her career. She viewed teaching as the main source of meaning in her life. An extremely dedicated professor, Chase believed that "the personality of the teacher is more important than her intellectual attainments" and that "if the teacher has no enthusiasm for teaching and for subject matter, her students will learn little." She was very excited about her field of expertise and hoped to similarly inspire her students.
Mary Ellen Chase has come to be known as one of the great American novelists. Much of her work was inspired by her childhood in Maine and several of her novels are autobiographical. The Goodly Heritage (1932) and A Goodly Fellowship (1939) are about her childhood and how she became a teacher, respectively. Chase also wrote several books for children and more than one of her novels became best-sellers.
Chase's popularity and skill at public speaking earned her many invitations to lecture around the country. She was awarded honorary degrees at the University of Maine, Bowdoin and Colby Colleges, Smith College, and Northeastern University. Her work was also acknowledged by the Women's National Book Association in 1956 when she was awarded the Constance Lindsay Skinner Award.
After her retirement in 1955 at the age of sixty-eight, Chase continued to live on-campus with her long-time companion, Eleanor Duckett, and her dog, Gregory. She spent summers in Maine at her home, "Windswept," and journeyed to England where she took Hebrew classes at Cambridge in order to better understand the Old Testament. She also taught two adult education seminars on the Bible at Radcliffe College. In 1968, Smith College acknowledged her dedication to the students and the College with a new dormitory, The Mary Ellen Chase House.
The Mary Ellen Chase Papers include biographical material including articles, correspondence, photographs, awards, financial information, reviews and writings. The latter part, which comprises the bulk of the collection, includes Chases's books, articles, and lectures in manuscript, typescript, galley and final published form. Among her books are translations of many of her titles into several languages.
The Smith College Archives houses other letters and photographs of Mary Ellen Chase that are not kept among the Mary Ellen Chase Papers, but with the papers of the other professors or students to whom the letters or pictures belonged. These are not listed in this finding aid, but can be located by consulting the card catalogue of the College Archives. The Mortimer Rare Book Room also holds some Mary Ellen Chase material, and likewise these holdings are not listed here, but can be found by consulting the catalogue of the Mortimer Rare Book Room.
This collection is organized into six series:
Biography
Photographs
Personal Correspondence
Professional Correspondence
Speeches
Publications
Information on Use
Terms of Access and Use
The papers are open for research according to the regulations of the Smith College Archives without any additional restrictions.
History of the Collection
The materials in the Mary Ellen Chase collection were given to the College Archives over a period of years between 1973 and 2001 by several donors, including Victor B. Harrison, Elizabeth Jacobsen, Helen K. Mills, Jenny V. Holtzermann, Deborah Wheeler, Professor Chase herself, and by her estate.
Additional Information
Related Material
42. Eleanor Shipley Duckett Papers
Mary Ellen Chase Papers, Mortimer Rare Book Room, Smith College
See card catalogue of the Smith College Archives
Books by Mary Ellen Chase in the Smith College Archives
Abby Aldrich Rockefeller. New York: The Macmillan Company, 1950
The Bible and the Common Reader. New York: The Macmillan Company, 1944 (2 copies)
The Bible and the Common Reader. Revised edition, 1952
Das Buch der Bucher, bie Bibel und der Mensch von Heute. Stuttgart: Hans E. Verlag
Constructive Theme Writing for College Freshman. New York: Henry Holt and Company, 1929
Constructive Theme Writing for College Freshman. Revised edition, 1938
Dawn in Lyonesse. New York: The Macmillan Company, 1938 (3 copies)
Dolly Moses: the Cat and the Clam Chowder. New York: W.W. Norton and Company, 1964
The Edge of Darkness. New York: W.W. Norton and Company, Inc. 1957
Am Rande der Dunkel-Heit. Munchen: Winkler-Verlag, 1964
Prakash-Reka. Bambay: Kailas Prakashan, 1959 (Marathi language) (also in Iranian, Bengali and another language -- possibly Arabic)
The Girl from the Big Horn Country. New York: A.L. Burt and Company, 1916
The Golden Ass and Other Essays. New York: Henry Holt and Company, 1929 (2 copies)
A Goodly Fellowship. New York: Macmillan and Company, 1939
La Joie d'Enseinger. Paris: Bantam Books, 1959
La Joie d'Enseinger. Bombay: Nav Lekhan Piublishers, 1962 (Marathi language)
La Joie d'Enseinger. Bombay: Ravani Prakashan Griha, n.d. (Gujarati language)
La Joie d'Enseinger. Tokyo: Kaitakusha Publishing Co, Ladder Edit., 1964 (in English with Japanese glosses) (also 2 Bengali editions)
A Goodly Heritage. New York: Henry Holt and Company, 1932
Haseen Miras. Lahore, Pakistan: West-Pak Publishing Company, Urdu-Bazar, n.d.
Haseen Miras. Madras, India: Kubera Printers, Ltd. 1932
A Goodly Heritage. Saigon, 1932
His Birthday. Boston: The Pilgrim Press, 1915
Jonathan Fisher, Maine Pastor. New York: The Macmillan Company, 1948 (2 copies)
A Journey to Boston. New York: W.W. Norton and Company, Inc. 1965
A Journey to Boston. Delhi: Shahazad Book House, 1967 (Urdu languge)
Life and Language in the Old Testament. New York: W.W. Norton and Company, Inc.1955
Life and Language in the Old Testament. New York: Gramercy Publishing Company, c.1955
Leben und Sprache in Alten Testament. Munchen: Winkler-Verlag, 1957
The Lovely Ambition. New York: W.W. Norton and Compnay, Inc. 1960
Ambiçao de Amor. Rio de Janiero: Lidador [1960]
Ambiçao de Amor. New Delhi: S.R. Suneja Publications, 1967 (Hindi language)
Mary Christmas. Boston: Little, Brown and Company, 1926
Mary Peters. New York: Macmillan Company, 1934 (2 copies)
Mary Peters. Wein im Phoenix Verlag, c.1946
Mary Peters. Bombay: Narayan Puranik, Kailas Prakashan, 1958 (Marathi language)
Mary Peters. Augsburg: Manu Verlag, 1947
Mary Peters. Allahabad: Desh Sewa Press, 1958 (Hindi language)
Look at America: New England. Boston: Houghton Mifflin Company, 1947
The Plum Tree. New York: Macmillan Company, 1949
Der Plaumenbaum/Eine Fahrt Nach Boston. Munchen: Winkler-Verlag, c.1949
The Prophets for the Common Reader. New York: W.W. Norton and Company, Inc. 1963
Readings from the Bible. New York: Macmillan Company, 1952
Richard Mansfield: Prince of Donkeys. New York: W.W. Norton and Company, Inc. 1964
Sailing the Seven Seas. New York: Dell, 1967
The Story of Lighthouses. New York: W.W. Norton and Company, Inc. 1965
Silas Crockett. New York: Macmillan Company, 1935
Thomas Hardy from Serial to Novel. New York: Russell and Russell, 1964
Thomas Hardy from Serial to Novel. University of Minnesota Press, 1927
This England. New York: Macmillan Company, 1936 (2 copies and a foreign language edition, possibly Urdu)
Victoria: a Pig in a Pram. New York: W.W. Norton, 1963
Virginia of Elk Creek Valley. New York: A. L. Burt Company, 1917
Uplands. Boston: Little Brown and Company, 1927
A Walk on an Iceberg. New York: W. W. Norton and Company, Inc. 1966
The White Gate. New York: W. W. Norton and Company, Inc. 1954
The White Gate. Maradana, Colombo: Messrs. Gunaratine and Company, n.d. (Sinhalese)
Windswept. New York: Macmillan Company, 1941
Stormhalen. Uppsala: J.A. Lindblads Forlag, 1943
Stormhalen. Armed services edition. Council on Books in Wartime. c. 1941
The Woman and the Sea. Tokyo: Kaitakusha, 1965 (in English with Japanese glosses)
Books About Mary Ellen Chase
Squire, Elienne. A Lantern in the Wind. Santa Barbara: Fithian Press, 1995
Chase, Evelyn Hyman. Feminist Convert: A Portrait of Mary Ellen Chase. Santa Barbara, CA: J. Daniel, 1988.
Articles About Mary Ellen Chase
Chase, Evelyn Hyman. "Mary Ellen Chase and the Incipient Feminist Movement," Smith Alumnae Quarterly (Summer 1987).
Hall, Virginia Smith, Down East Today (1938)
Kingman, Lee. "Pamela's Socks and the Roman Emperors," Vogue essay contest (date?)
Squire, Elienne. "A Famous Author and Teacher," Smith Alumnae Quarterly (Summer 1987).
Mary Ellen Chase Material at other Repositories
Columbia University. Rare Book and Manuscript Library. Women's National Book Association Records, 1917-1989. Includes M.E. Chase correspondence. There is also correspondence in the Amy Loveman collection.
Harvard Divinity School. Andover-Harvard Theological Library. Robert Henry Pfeiffer Papers, 1911-1958. Includes M.E. Chase correspondence.
Iowa State University, Library, Special Collections. Frederick William Lorch papers, 1857-1966. Includes M.E. Chase correspondence.
Syracuse University, George Arents Research Library for Special Collections. Robert Silliman Hillyer papers, 1902-1963. Includes M.E. Chase correspondence.
University of Iowa Libraries. Special Collections Department. Letter to Prof. Grover. Northampton, MA, declining an invitation because of a trip (Nov. 30, 19??).
University of Maine. Special Collections. Approximately one inch of "Letters written by Miss Chase to Dr. Hugh Stalker, writings, notebooks, portrait, and clippings" dating from 1940-69. Given by Chase in two accessions, while alive then again from her estate.
University of Michigan, Ann Arbor. Bentley Historical Library. Frank Addison Manny papers, 1890-1955. Includes M.E. Chase correspondence.
University of Minnesota. Manuscripts Division. Prophets for the Common Reader, manuscript, 1962.
University of New England. Maine Women Writers Project. Approximately 3 linear feet of "Correspondence, documents, and clippings relating to Miss Chase's publications (1909-1964)". There is also correspondence in the Coatsworth Collection.
University of Rochester, Rush Rhees Library, Department of Rare Books, Manuscripts and Archives. Manuscripts Collection Ch - Cl, 1731-1980. Includes M.E. Chase correspondence.
Yale University. Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library. Wallace Notestein papers, 1899-1969, and Kathryn Hulme papers, 1846-1981. Both include M.E. Chase correspondence.
- Series I. BIOGRAPHY
  - General 1930-1957, undated (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Newsclippings 1926-1973, undated (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - "The Diamond Jubille of Mary Ellen Chase," Colby Library Quarterly March 1962 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Obituaries and other Posthumous Accounts 1973-1995, undated (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Memorabilia 1944-1973, undated (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Check Registers 1950-1964 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Press Releases 1929-1967, undated (Box 1, Folder 7)
- Series II. PHOTOGRAPHS
  - Portraits 1920-1957, undated (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Portraits-Stahlberg Portraits 1933, 1941, undated (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Portraits-Dining Room Photos ca. 1960s (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Chase and Eleanor Duckett 1949, 1961, undated (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Events 1933-1965 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Family and Friends 1893, 1951, undated (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Houses undated (Box 1, Folder 13)
- Series III. PERSONAL CORRESPONDENCE
  - Jane Brooks 1961 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Virginia Callahan 1965-1971, undated (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Newton K. Chase 1971 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Virginia Gildersleeve 1962 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Margaret Grierson 1966 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - J.D. Holtzermann 1922-1936, undated (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Edward Kessler 1960 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Marine Leland undated (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Ann and Robert MacMurphy 1927, 1929 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Elizabeth "Betty" Pence McKibben 1938-1963 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Thomas Corwin Mendenhall 1966 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Virginia Chase Perkins undated (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Florence Perry 1942 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Deborah Wheeler 1952-1968, undated (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Miscellaneous 1945-1972, undated (Box 2, Folder 8)
- Series IV. PROFESSIONAL CORRESPONDENCE
  - George C. Connor, re: Windswept 1945 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - re Rabbi Abraham Feldman/Bible and Common Reader 1948 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Mrs. Noels 1934 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Florence Snow 1930-1949 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Katharine Starrett Whitton and Helen Starrett Dinwiddle 1940 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Fan Mail 1941-1974 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Miscellaneous 1940-1979 (Box 2, Folder 15)
- Series V. SPEECHES
  - Chapel talks 1937,1941, undated (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Smith College Alumnae Council Feb 8, 1952 (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Postscript to the Writing of a Novel Friends of the Library, Smith College April 20, 1957 (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - First Things First, "Fight for Freedom," Meeting of the Hampshire County Committee Nov. 27, 1941 (Box 2, Folder 19)
- Series VI PUBLICATIONS
  - General 1941-1965 (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - "Abby Aldrich Rockefeller" Good Housekeeping June 1950 (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - The Abundant Life in Books Sept. 1936 (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - Alice M. Holden obituary undated (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - "Are We Afraid of Being Alone?" Woman's Day undated (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - "The Author and His Reader" 1935 (Box 2, Folder 25)
  - Dolly Moses 1964 (Box 2, Folder 26)
  - "Elizabeth Cutter Morrow" Feb. 1955 (Box 2, Folder 27)
  - in memory of Victoria Schrager Oct. 27, 1943 (Box 2, Folder 28)
  - Inaugural Date Oct. 15, [1957] (Box 2, Folder 29)
  - Jonathan Fisher 1946 (Box 2, Folder 30)
  - "A Kitchen Parnassus," Atlantic Monthly Aug, 1926 (Box 2, Folder 31)
  - Life and Language in the Old Testament: manuscript notebooks Apr. 24, 1955 (Box 2, Folder 32-34)
  - Life and Language in the Old Testament: manuscript notebooks Apr. 24, 1955 (Box 3)
  - "Life in Books," Smith undated (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - "Old Time Christmases in Maine" Ladies Home Journal Dec. 1937 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - "Our Educational Heritage" Journal of the AAUW Jan. 1940 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - The Needs of Smith College 1939 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - A Pig in a Pram (original manuscript) ca. 1963 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - A Pig in a Pram (corrected typescripts) ca. 1963 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - A Pig in a Pram (marked galley) Apr. 2, 1963 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - The Plum Tree (revised manuscript) 1949 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Recipe for a Magic Childhood pamphlet and article 1951 and 1952 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Richard Mansfield (marked typescript) ca. 1963 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Richard Mansfield (marked galley) Oct. 21, 1963 (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Sarah Orne Jewett (typescript) undated (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - "She Misses Some Goals, " Life Dec, 1956 (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - Smith College - A Definition (book and typescript) 1968 (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - The Story of Lighthouses (typescript) Jan. 7, 1965 (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - The Story of Lighthouses (marked galley) ca. 1965 (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - "Taxi Driver 63," Delineator Feb. 1939 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - A Walk on an Iceberg (marked typescript) undated (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - "When You Go Home," Coronet Dec. 1952 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - The White Gate (manuscript notebooks) 1954 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Windswept (drawings, photographs and letters) c.1941-1946 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - "You Become Someone - Alone" Readers' Digest Mar. 1962 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Reviews of publications by M.E.C. c.1929-1965 (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Reviews, by M.E.C, of publications c.1928-1966 (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Edge of Darkness-general 1957 (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - Edge of Darkness-original manuscripts, I and II Jan.12-Mar.5, 1957 (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - Edge of Darkness-original manuscripts, III and IV 1957 (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - Edge of Darkness-revised manuscripts, I-IV Jan.12- Mar.10, 1957 (Box 4, Folder 12)
  - Edge of Darkness-three manuscript books containing final revisions Mar.18-31, 1957 (Box 5)
  - The Lovely Ambition: corrected author's galley I undated (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - The Lovely Ambition: corrected author's galley II Dec. 31, 1959 (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - The Lovely Ambition: galleys: title page ca. 1960 (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - The Lovely Ambition: marked and corrected typescript Dec. 2, 1959 (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Prophets for the Common Reader: manuscript (incomplete) undated (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - Prophets for the Common Reader: first typescript ca. 1963 (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - Prophets for the Common Reader: second manuscript (complete) ca. 1963 (Box 6, Folder 3)